<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Feature Engineering on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/categories/feature-engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Feature Engineering on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/feature-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vectorize ROC Curve for Bayesian Models</title>
      <link>/vectorize_roc_curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vectorize_roc_curve/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we present a simple example to illustrate how to vectorize the ROC curve computation over a Bayesian model. This is helpful when we want to compute the ROC curve using the implementations from scikit-learn. We use the classical moons dataset to generate the data and fit a Gaussian process models similarly as the previous post Scikit-Learn Example in PyMC: Gaussian Process Classifier.
Prepare Notebook import arviz as az import matplotlib.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to vectorize an scikit-learn transformer over a numpy array?</title>
      <link>/vectorize_sklearn_transformer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vectorize_sklearn_transformer/</guid>
      <description>In this short post, I show how to vectorize an scikit-learn transformer over a numpy array. That is, how to apply a transformer along a specific axes of a numpy array. I have found this to be particularly useful when working with output sample posterior distributions from a bayesian model where I want to apply a transformer to each sample. This is not particularly difficult, but I always forget how to do it, so I thought I would write it down once and for all 😄.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
