<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian, Gaussian Processes on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/categories/bayesian-gaussian-processes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian, Gaussian Processes on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/bayesian-gaussian-processes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Hierarchical Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>/hierarchical_hsgp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/hierarchical_hsgp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this notebook, we want to explore some ideas on hierarchical Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes following the fantastic exposition of the PyMC example notebook: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pymc.io/projects/examples/en/latest/gaussian_processes/HSGP-Advanced.html&#34;&gt;“Gaussian Processes: HSGP Advanced Usage”&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bwengals&#34;&gt;Bill Engels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AlexAndorra&#34;&gt;Alexandre Andorra&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ferrine&#34;&gt;Maxim Kochurov&lt;/a&gt;. I can only recommend to read the notebook and the references therein!&#xA;For an introduction to Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes, please see my introductory blog post: &lt;a href=&#34;https://juanitorduz.github.io/hsgp_intro/&#34;&gt;“A Conceptual and Practical Introduction to Hilbert Space GPs Approximation Methods”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation&lt;/strong&gt;: In many applications, one is interested in understanding the dynamic effect of one variable on another. For example, in marketing, one is interested in efficiency across many channels on sales (or conversions) as a function of time. For such a purpose, one typically uses a time-varying regression model with time-varying coefficients (for a simple example, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://juanitorduz.github.io/bikes_gp/&#34;&gt;“Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Hilbert Space Gaussian Process Approximation”&lt;/a&gt;). The main challenge is that, if not done carefully, the model will easily overfit the data. One can use a hierarchical model with a global component and a group-specific component to overcome this. The global component will capture the overall trend, while the group-specific component will capture the idiosyncratic behavior of each group. As a side effect, we will gain some regularization effect that will help to avoid overfitting. For the marketing example above, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pymc-labs.com/blog-posts/&#34;&gt;PyMC Labs&lt;/a&gt; has successfully applied this approach in the context of media mix modeling: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pymc-labs.com/blog-posts/modelling-changes-marketing-effectiveness-over-time/&#34;&gt;“Bayesian Media Mix Models: Modelling changes in marketing effectiveness over time”&lt;/a&gt;. This hierarchical approach was motivated by the work &lt;a href=&#34;https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-14-252&#34;&gt;“Hierarchical Bayesian modeling of gene expression time series across irregularly sampled replicates and clusters”&lt;/a&gt;. Here is a schematic diagram of the hierarchical approach (taken from the paper):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Conceptual and Practical Introduction to Hilbert Space GPs Approximation Methods</title>
      <link>/hsgp_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/hsgp_intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this notebook, we explore the (conceptual) ideas and (practical) implementation details of the &lt;em&gt;Hilbert Space&lt;/em&gt; approximation for Gaussian processes introduced in the article &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11222-019-09886-w&#34;&gt;“Hilbert space methods for reduced-rank Gaussian process regression”&lt;/a&gt; by Arno Solin and Simo Särkkä. We do not go deep into the mathematical details (proofs) but focus on the core ideas to help us understand the main concepts guiding the technical implementation. We provide examples, both in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyro-ppl/numpyro&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;NumPyro&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pymc-devs/pymc&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PyMC&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so that users can learn from cross-framework comparison so that we abstract the core ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
