<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian, Gaussian Processes on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/categories/bayesian-gaussian-processes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian, Gaussian Processes on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/bayesian-gaussian-processes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Hierarchical Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>/hierarchical_hsgp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hierarchical_hsgp/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we want to explore some ideas on hierarchical Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes following the fantastic exposition of the PyMC example notebook: “Gaussian Processes: HSGP Advanced Usage” by Bill Engels, Alexandre Andorra and Maxim Kochurov. I can only recommend to read the notebook and the references therein! For an introduction to Hilbert Space Gaussian Processes, please see my introductory blog post: “A Conceptual and Practical Introduction to Hilbert Space GPs Approximation Methods”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Conceptual and Practical Introduction to Hilbert Space GPs Approximation Methods</title>
      <link>/hsgp_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hsgp_intro/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we explore the (conceptual) ideas and (practical) implementation details of the Hilbert Space approximation for Gaussian processes introduced in the article “Hilbert space methods for reduced-rank Gaussian process regression” by Arno Solin and Simo Särkkä. We do not go deep into the mathematical details (proofs) but focus on the core ideas to help us understand the main concepts guiding the technical implementation. We provide examples, both in NumPyro and PyMC, so that users can learn from cross-framework comparison so that we abstract the core ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
