<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python, numpyro on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/tags/python-numpyro/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python, numpyro on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/python-numpyro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Counting the Number of Kitas per PLZ in Berlin using a Hierarchical Bayesian Model</title>
      <link>/kitas-hierarchical/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/kitas-hierarchical/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the continuation of data gathering and data analysis post Open Data: Berlin Kitas. In this second part we use the data gathered to model the number of Kitas per PLZ in Berlin using a hierarchical bayesian model. The hierarchy is defined by the Berlin districts. The objective is to develop a sound basic model which can be enhanced in the future with a richer data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Hierarchical Model with NumPyro: Cookie Chips Example</title>
      <link>/cookies_example_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/cookies_example_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>This notebook presents a simple example of a hierarchical model using NumPyro. The example is based on the cookie chips example in presented in the post Introduction to Bayesian Modeling with PyMC3. There are many great resources regarding bayesian hierarchical model and probabilistic programming NumPyro. This notebook aims to provide a succinct simple example to get started.
Remark: Well, the real reason is that I want to get acquainted other probabilistic programming libraries in order to abstract the core principles of probabilistic programming.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
