<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python, pymc on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/tags/python-pymc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python, pymc on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/python-pymc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Hilbert Space Gaussian Process Approximation</title>
      <link>/bikes_gp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bikes_gp/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we present an example of a regression model with time varying coefficients using Gaussian processes. In particular, we use a Hilbert space Gaussian process approximation in pymc to speed up the computations (see HSGP). We continue using the bikes dataset from the previous posts (Exploring Tools for Interpretable Machine Learning and Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Gaussian Random Walk in PyMC). Please refer to those posts for more details on the dataset, EDA and base models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Gaussian Random Walk in PyMC</title>
      <link>/bikes_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bikes_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we want to illustrate how to use PyMC to fit a time-varying coefficient regression model. The motivation comes from post Exploring Tools for Interpretable Machine Learning where we studied a time series problem, regarding the prediction of the number of bike rentals, from a machine learning perspective. Concretely, we fitted and compared two machine learning models: a linear regression with interactions and a gradient boost model (XGBoost).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
