<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geometry on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/categories/geometry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geometry on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/geometry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>\(S^1\)-Equivariant Dirac operators on the Hopf Fibration</title>
      <link>/2018/11/11/hopf_fibration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/11/hopf_fibration/</guid>
      <description>In this post I want to present some notes around the fundamentals of the Hopf fibration \(\pi: S^3 \longrightarrow S^2\) which I started writing during my PhD period at Humboldt Universität zu Berlin. First, I describe its definition and I show that it is a non-trivial map by computing its first Chern class. Then I give a detailed treatment of the construction of two important Dirac-type operators: the Hodge-de Rham and the spin-Dirac.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Induced Dirac-Schrödinger operators on semi-free circle quotients</title>
      <link>/2017/11/11/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/11/phd/</guid>
      <description>In this post I present the results of my Mathematics PhD thesis which I wrote under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Jochen Brüning at Humbolt Universität zu Berlin. I gratefully acknowledge the financial support of the Berlin Mathematical School and the research project SFB 647: Space - Time - Matter
Abstract:
John Lott has computed an integer-valued signature for the orbit space of a compact orientable \((4k+1)\) manifold with a semi-free \(S^1\)-action, which is a homotopy invariant of that space, but he did not construct a Dirac type operator which has this signature as its index.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dirac operator on the 2-sphere</title>
      <link>/2017/06/29/the-dirac-operator-on-the-2-sphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/29/the-dirac-operator-on-the-2-sphere/</guid>
      <description>The objective of this post is to explore MathJax, a JavaScript display engine for LaTeX. Being my first post writen with this tool, I want to present a short but fun example: I will give a description of the explicit computation of the spin-Dirac operator (of the unique complex spinor bundle!) on the 2-sphere \(S^2\) equipped with the standar round metric. A more detailed treatment can be found in my expository paper.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>