<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python, Numpyro, Pymc on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/tags/python-numpyro-pymc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python, Numpyro, Pymc on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/python-numpyro-pymc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Exponential Smoothing Model</title>
      <link>/hierarchical_exponential_smoothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/hierarchical_exponential_smoothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we experiment with a hierarchical exponential smoothing forecasting model, extending the ideas from the univariate case presented in the blog post &lt;a href=&#34;https://juanitorduz.github.io/exponential_smoothing_numpyro/&#34;&gt;“Notes on Exponential Smoothing with NumPyro”&lt;/a&gt;. We use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyro-ppl/numpyro&#34;&gt;NumPyro&lt;/a&gt; and compare the NUTS and SVI results. For such a purpose, we use &lt;strong&gt;Continuous Ranked Probability Score&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com/crps-a-scoring-function-for-bayesian-machine-learning-models-dd55a7a337a8&#34;&gt;CRPS&lt;/a&gt;). We also compare these forecasts with univariate statistical models like Holt-Winters, AutoETS and Seasonal Naive from the great &lt;a href=&#34;https://nixtlaverse.nixtla.io/statsforecast/index.html&#34;&gt;Statsforecast&lt;/a&gt; package. These baseline models are, in general, hard to beat!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Censoring Data Modeling</title>
      <link>/censoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/censoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this notebook, we explore how we can use Bayesian modeling to estimate the parameters of a censored data set. These datasets are common in many fields, including survival analysis and supply chain management. I was motivated to write this notebook after reading the excellent blog post &lt;a href=&#34;https://kylejcaron.github.io/posts/censored_demand/2024-02-06-censored-demand.html&#34;&gt;“Modeling Anything With First Principles: Demand under extreme stockouts”&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://kylejcaron.github.io/&#34;&gt;Kyle Caron&lt;/a&gt; where he uses these techniques to model and balance demand under extreme stockouts and other constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
