<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python, bayesian, tfp on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/tags/python-bayesian-tfp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python, bayesian, tfp on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/python-bayesian-tfp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Simple Bayesian Linear Regression with TensorFlow Probability</title>
      <link>/tfp_lm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tfp_lm/</guid>
      <description>In this post we show how to fit a simple linear regression model using TensorFlow Probability by replicating the first example on the getting started guide for PyMC3. We are going to use Auto-Batched Joint Distributions as they simplify the model specification considerably. Moreover, there is a great resource to get deeper into this type of distribution: Auto-Batched Joint Distributions: A Gentle Tutorial, which I strongly recommend (see this post to get a brief introduction on TensorFlow probability distributions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Hamiltonian Monte Carlo Example with TensorFlow Probability</title>
      <link>/tfp_hcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tfp_hcm/</guid>
      <description>In this post we want to revisit a simple bayesian inference example worked out in this blog post. This time we want to use TensorFlow Probability (TFP) instead of PyMC3.
References:
 Statistical Rethinking is an amazing reference for Bayesian analysis. It also has a sequence of online lectures freely available on YouTube.
 An introduction to probabilistic programming, now available in TensorFlow Probability
 There are many examples on the TensorFlow’s GitHub repository.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
