<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/categories/bayesian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/bayesian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU - Part III.</title>
      <link>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku_3/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we continue our simulation study for elasticities, see:
 Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU - Part I
 Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU - Part II
  for an introduction to the problem and some models. We extend the covariance model to allow two covariance components on both the intercepts and slopes (coefficient of the median_ income variable). Also, to abstract from a specific framework, we do the implementation in NumPyro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Exponential Smoothing Model</title>
      <link>/hierarchical_exponential_smoothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hierarchical_exponential_smoothing/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, we experiment with a hierarchical exponential smoothing forecasting model, extending the ideas from the univariate case presented in the blog post “Notes on Exponential Smoothing with NumPyro”. We use NumPyro and compare the NUTS and SVI results. For such a purpose, we use Continuous Ranked Probability Score (CRPS). We also compare these forecasts with univariate statistical models like Holt-Winters, AutoETS and Seasonal Naive from the great Statsforecast package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Censoring Data Modeling</title>
      <link>/censoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/censoring/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we explore how we can use Bayesian modeling to estimate the parameters of a censored data set. These datasets are common in many fields, including survival analysis and supply chain management. I was motivated to write this notebook after reading the excellent blog post “Modeling Anything With First Principles: Demand under extreme stockouts” by Kyle Caron where he uses these techniques to model and balance demand under extreme stockouts and other constraints.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Inflated TSB Model</title>
      <link>/zi_tsb_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/zi_tsb_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>After going through the fundamentals of the TSB Method for Intermittent Time Series Forecasting in NumPyro in the previous notebook, we explore a variation of it that might be useful for certain applications. In a nutshell, we keep the same model structure of the TSB model, but we modify the likelihood function to account for the sparsity of the time series. Concretely, we replace the classic Gaussian likelihood function with a zero-inflated Negative Binomial likelihood function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TSB Method for Intermittent Time Series Forecasting in NumPyro</title>
      <link>/tsb_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tsb_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we provide a NumPyro implementation of the TSB (Teunter, Syntetos and Babai) method for forecasting intermittent time series. The TSB method is similar to the Croston’s method in the sense that is constructs two different time series out of the original one and then forecast each of them separately, so that the final forecast is generated by combining the forecasts of the two time series. The main difference between the two methods is that the TSB method uses the demand probability instead of the demand periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Croston&#39;s Method for Intermittent Time Series Forecasting in NumPyro</title>
      <link>/croston_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/croston_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we will implement Croston’s method for intermittent demand forecasting using NumPyro. Croston’s method is a popular forecasting method for intermittent demand data, which is characterized by a large number of zero values. The method is based on the idea of separating the demand size and the demand interval, and then forecasting them separately using simple exponential smoothing. We therefore can leverage on top of the previous post Notes on Exponential Smoothing with NumPyro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on an ARMA(1, 1) Model with NumPyro</title>
      <link>/arma_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/arma_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>This are some notes on how to implement an ARMA(1, 1) model using NumPyro for time series forecasting. The ARMA(1, 1) model is given by
\[y_t = \mu + \phi y_{t-1} + \theta \varepsilon_{t-1} + \varepsilon_t\]
where \(y_t\) is the time series, \(\mu\) is the mean, \(\phi\) is the autoregressive parameter, \(\theta\) is the moving average parameter, and \(\varepsilon_t\) is a white noise process with mean zero and variance \(\sigma^2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Exponential Smoothing with NumPyro</title>
      <link>/exponential_smoothing_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/exponential_smoothing_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>This notebook serves as personal notes on NumPyro’s implementation of the classic exponential smoothing forecasting method. I use Example: Holt-Winters Exponential Smoothing. The strategy is to go into the nitty-gritty details of the code presented in the example from the documentation: “Example: Holt-Winters Exponential Smoothing”. In particular, I want to understand the auto-regressive components using the scan function, which always confuses me 😅. After reproducing the example from the documentation, we go a step further and extend the algorithm to include a damped trend.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media Mix Model and Experimental Calibration: A Simulation Study</title>
      <link>/mmm_roas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/mmm_roas/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook, we present a complete simulation study of the media mix model (MMM) and experimental calibration method presented in the paper “Media Mix Model Calibration With Bayesian Priors”, by Zhang, et al., where the authors propose a convenient parametrization the regression model in terms of the ROAs (return on advertising spend) instead of the classical regression (beta) coefficients. The benefit of this parametrization is that it allows for using Bayesian priors on the ROAS, which typically come from previous experiments or domain knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flax and NumPyro Toy Example</title>
      <link>/flax_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/flax_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook I want to experiment with the numpyro/contrib/module.py module which allow us to integrate Flax models with NumPyro models. I am interested in this because I want to experiment with complex bayesian models with larger datasets.
Most of the main components can be found in the great blog post Bayesian Neural Networks with Flax and Numpyro. The author takes a different path working directly with potentials, but he also points out the recent addition of the numpyro/contrib/module.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Series Modeling with HSGP: Baby Births Example</title>
      <link>/birthdays/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/birthdays/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we want to reproduce a classical example of using Gaussian processes to model time series data: The birthdays data set. I first encountered this example in the seminal book Chapter 21, Bayesian Data Analysis (Third edition) when learning about the subject. One thing I rapidly realized was that fitting these types of models in practice is very computationally expensive and sometimes almost infeasible for real industry applications where the data size is larger than all of these academic examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Parametric Product Life Cycle Modeling</title>
      <link>/iphone_trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/iphone_trends/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we present an example of how to use a combination of Bayesian hierarchical models and the non-parametric methods , namely bayesian additive trees (BART), to model the product life cycles. This approach is motivated by previous work in cohort analysis, see here.
As a case study we use the Google search index (trends) data for iPhones worldwide. We use the data of four different models to predict the development of the latest iPhone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NumPyro with Pathfinder</title>
      <link>/numpyro_pathfinder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/numpyro_pathfinder/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we describe how to use blackjax’s pathfinder implementation to do inference with a numpyro model.
I am simply putting some pieces together from the following resources (strongly recommended to read):
References:
 Blackjax docs: Use with Numpyro models Blackjax Sampling Book: Pathfinder Numpyro Issue #1485 PyMC Experimental - Pathfinder Pathfinder: Parallel quasi-Newton variational inference  What and Why Pathfinder? From the paper’s abstract:
 What?   We propose Pathfinder, a variational method for approximately sampling from differentiable log densities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU - Part II.</title>
      <link>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku_2/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we go deeper into the last covariance model presented in the previous blog post Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU. In particular we describe how to generate posterior predictive samples from an unseen region by the model. This can be useful for scenario planning: once can simulated outcome quantities from price ranges through the elasticity estimates (with uncertainty!)
We strongly recommend reading the previous blog post before reading this one as we will skip the EDA and baseline model comparison parts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel Elasticities for a Single SKU - Part I.</title>
      <link>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/multilevel_elasticities_single_sku/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook I want to experiment with some basic models for price elasticity estimation in the simple context of a simple sku across multiple stores and regions. The motivation is to have a concrete example of the elasticity models presented in the Chapter 11: Big Data Pricing Models of the book Pricing Analytics by Walter R. Paczkowski.
Elasticity Definition Here I provide a very succinct definition of elasticity (there is a vast literature on this topic, see the reference above).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Hilbert Space Gaussian Process Approximation</title>
      <link>/bikes_gp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bikes_gp/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we present an example of a regression model with time varying coefficients using Gaussian processes. In particular, we use a Hilbert space Gaussian process approximation in pymc to speed up the computations (see HSGP). We continue using the bikes dataset from the previous posts (Exploring Tools for Interpretable Machine Learning and Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Gaussian Random Walk in PyMC). Please refer to those posts for more details on the dataset, EDA and base models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Counting the Number of Kitas per PLZ in Berlin using a Hierarchical Bayesian Model</title>
      <link>/kitas-hierarchical/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/kitas-hierarchical/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the continuation of data gathering and data analysis post Open Data: Berlin Kitas. In this second part we use the data gathered to model the number of Kitas per PLZ in Berlin using a hierarchical bayesian model. The hierarchy is defined by the Berlin districts. The objective is to develop a sound basic model which can be enhanced in the future with a richer data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Hierarchical Model with NumPyro: Cookie Chips Example</title>
      <link>/cookies_example_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/cookies_example_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>This notebook presents a simple example of a hierarchical model using NumPyro. The example is based on the cookie chips example in presented in the post Introduction to Bayesian Modeling with PyMC3. There are many great resources regarding bayesian hierarchical model and probabilistic programming NumPyro. This notebook aims to provide a succinct simple example to get started.
Remark: Well, the real reason is that I want to get acquainted other probabilistic programming libraries in order to abstract the core principles of probabilistic programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scikit-Learn Example in PyMC: Gaussian Process Classifier</title>
      <link>/sklearn_pymc_classifier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sklearn_pymc_classifier/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we want to describe how to port a couple of classification examples from scikit-learn’s documentation (classifier comparison) to PyMC. We focus in the classical moons synthetic dataset.
Prepare Notebook import arviz as az import matplotlib.pyplot as plt import numpy as np import pandas as pd import pymc as pm import pymc.sampling_jax import seaborn as sns from sklearn.datasets import make_moons from sklearn.metrics import accuracy_score from sklearn.model_selection import train_test_split plt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Control in PyMC</title>
      <link>/synthetic_control_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/synthetic_control_pymc/</guid>
      <description>Synthetic control can be considered “the most important innovation in the policy evaluation literature in the last few years” (see The State of Applied Econometrics: Causality and Policy Evaluation by Susan Athey and Guido W. Imbens).
 In this notebook we provide an example of how to implement a synthetic control problem in PyMC to answer a “what if this had happened?” type of question in the context of causal inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Short Time Series with Prior Knowledge in PyMC</title>
      <link>/short_time_series_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/short_time_series_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook I want to reproduce in PyMC the methodology described in the amazing blog post Modeling Short Time Series with Prior Knowledge by Tim Radtke to forecast short time series using bayesian transfer learning 🚀. The main idea is to transfer information (e.g. long term seasonality) from a long time series to a short time series via prior distributions. Tim’s blog post treats a very concrete example where all the concepts become very concrete.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Regression Coefficients via Gaussian Random Walk in PyMC</title>
      <link>/bikes_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bikes_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we want to illustrate how to use PyMC to fit a time-varying coefficient regression model. The motivation comes from post Exploring Tools for Interpretable Machine Learning where we studied a time series problem, regarding the prediction of the number of bike rentals, from a machine learning perspective. Concretely, we fitted and compared two machine learning models: a linear regression with interactions and a gradient boost model (XGBoost).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PyConDE &amp; PyData Berlin 2022: Introduction to Uplift Modeling</title>
      <link>/uplift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/uplift/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we present a simple example of uplift modeling estimation via meta-models using causalml and scikit-uplift. For a more detailed introduction to uplift modeling, see:
 Diemert, Eustache, et.al. (2020) “A Large Scale Benchmark for Uplift Modeling”
 Gutierrez, P., &amp;amp; Gérardy, J. Y. (2017). “Causal Inference and Uplift Modelling: A Review of the Literature”
 Karlsson, H. (2019) “Uplift Modeling: Identifying Optimal Treatment Group Allocation and Whom to Contact to Maximize Return on Investment”</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gamma-Gamma Model of Monetary Value in PyMC</title>
      <link>/gamma_gamma_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gamma_gamma_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we describe how to fit Fader’s and Hardie’s gamma-gamma model presented in the paper “RFM and CLV: Using Iso-value Curves for Customer Base Analysis” and the note “The Gamma-Gamma Model of Monetary Value”. The approach is very similar as the one presented in the previous post BG/NBD Model in PyMC where we simply ported the log-likelihood of the lifetimes package from numpy to pytensor.
Prepare Notebook import arviz as az import matplotlib.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BG/NBD Model in PyMC</title>
      <link>/bg_nbd_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bg_nbd_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we show how to port the BG/NBD model from the the lifetimes (developed mainly by Cameron Davidson-Pilon) package to pymc. The BG/NBD model, introduced in the seminal paper “Counting Your Customers” the Easy Way: An Alternative to the Pareto/NBD Model by Peter S. Fader, Bruce G. S. Hardie and Ka Lok Lee in 2005, is used to
 predict future purchasing patterns, which can then serve as an input into “lifetime value” calculations, in the “non-contractual” setting (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media Effect Estimation with PyMC: Adstock, Saturation &amp; Diminishing Returns</title>
      <link>/pymc_mmm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/pymc_mmm/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we present a concrete example of estimating the media effects via bayesian methods, following the strategy outlined in Google’s paper Jin, Yuxue, et al. “Bayesian methods for media mix modeling with carryover and shape effects.” (2017). This example can be considered the continuation of the post Media Effect Estimation with Orbit’s KTR Model. However, it is not strictly necessary to read before as we make this notebook self-contained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media Effect Estimation with Orbit&#39;s KTR Model</title>
      <link>/orbit_mmm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/orbit_mmm/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook we want to experiment to the new KTR model included in the new orbit’s release (1.1). In particular, we are interested in its applications to media effects estimation in the context of media mix modeling. This is one of the applications for the KTR model by the Uber’s team, see the corresponding paper Edwin, Ng, et al. “Bayesian Time Varying Coefficient Model with Applications to Marketing Mix Modeling”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unobserved Components Model as a Bayesian Model with PyMC</title>
      <link>/uc_pymc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/uc_pymc/</guid>
      <description>In this notebook I want to deep-dive into the idea of wrapping a statsmodels UnobservedComponents model as a bayesian model with PyMC described in the (great!) post Fast Bayesian estimation of SARIMAX models. This is a nice excuse to get into some internals of how PyMC works. I hope this can serve as a complement to the original post mentioned above. This post has two parts: In the first one we fit a UnobservedComponents model to a simulated time series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Bayesian Linear Regression with TensorFlow Probability</title>
      <link>/tfp_lm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tfp_lm/</guid>
      <description>In this post we show how to fit a simple linear regression model using TensorFlow Probability by replicating the first example on the getting started guide for PyMC3. We are going to use Auto-Batched Joint Distributions as they simplify the model specification considerably. Moreover, there is a great resource to get deeper into this type of distribution: Auto-Batched Joint Distributions: A Gentle Tutorial, which I strongly recommend (see this post to get a brief introduction on TensorFlow probability distributions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Hamiltonian Monte Carlo Example with TensorFlow Probability</title>
      <link>/tfp_hcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tfp_hcm/</guid>
      <description>In this post we want to revisit a simple bayesian inference example worked out in this blog post. This time we want to use TensorFlow Probability (TFP) instead of PyMC3.
References:
 Statistical Rethinking is an amazing reference for Bayesian analysis. It also has a sequence of online lectures freely available on YouTube.
 An introduction to probabilistic programming, now available in TensorFlow Probability
 There are many examples on the TensorFlow’s GitHub repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Bayesian Modeling with PyMC3</title>
      <link>/intro_pymc3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/intro_pymc3/</guid>
      <description>We give an introduction to PyMC3, a probabilistic programming framework written in Python. We revise the basic mahematical theory and present two concrete examples.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
