<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python, Bayes, Numpyro, Flax, Marketing on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</title>
    <link>/tags/python-bayes-numpyro-flax-marketing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python, Bayes, Numpyro, Flax, Marketing on Dr. Juan Camilo Orduz</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/python-bayes-numpyro-flax-marketing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cohort Revenue Retention Analysis with Flax and NumPyro</title>
      <link>/revenue_retention_numpyro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/revenue_retention_numpyro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this notebook we present an alternative implementation of the cohort-revenue-retention model presented in the blog post &lt;a href=&#34;https://juanitorduz.github.io/revenue_retention/&#34;&gt;Cohort Revenue &amp;amp; Retention Analysis: A Bayesian Approach&lt;/a&gt; where we show how to replace the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pymc-devs/pymc-bart&#34;&gt;BART&lt;/a&gt; retention component with a general neural network implemented with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/flax&#34;&gt;Flax&lt;/a&gt;. This allows faster inference, as we can use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyro-ppl/numpyro&#34;&gt;NumPyro&lt;/a&gt;’s NUTS sampler or any of the stochastic variational inference (SVI) algorithms available. We could even use a wider family of samplers using the newly released package &lt;a href=&#34;https://jax-ml.github.io/bayeux/&#34;&gt;Bayeux&lt;/a&gt; or the great &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blackjax-devs/blackjax&#34;&gt;BlackJax&lt;/a&gt; (see for example, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blackjax-devs.github.io/sampling-book/models/mlp.html&#34;&gt;MLP Classifier Example&lt;/a&gt;).&#xA;We use the same simulated dataset to be able to compare the approaches. Overall, the retention and revenue in and out-of sample predictions, as well as the credible intervals are very similar to the ones obtained with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pymc-devs/pymc-bart&#34;&gt;BART&lt;/a&gt; model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
